<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Harrand</title><link>https://harrand.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Harrand</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://harrand.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>About Me</title><link>https://harrand.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://harrand.github.io/about/</guid><description>Harrand is my pseudonym, but I also go by Harry. You can call me whichever you prefer I am a game engine programmer, in and outside of industry. Currently I work on the Cobra engine at Frontier Developments. Outside of work, I work on the Topaz engine by myself. You can find my CV here You&amp;rsquo;ll find my videos and livestreams on my YouTube channel, although note that I have no upload/streaming schedule and the content that I provide is not always programming related.</description><content>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Harrand is my pseudonym, but I also go by Harry. You can call me whichever you prefer&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I am a game engine programmer, in and outside of industry.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Currently I work on the Cobra engine at Frontier Developments.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Outside of work, I work on the Topaz engine by myself.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You can find my CV &lt;a href="../CV.pdf">here&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You&amp;rsquo;ll find my videos and livestreams on &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/theharryh666">my YouTube channel&lt;/a>, although note that I have no upload/streaming schedule and the content that I provide is not always programming related.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Harrand">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/gh.svg" alt="Github Profile" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/theharryh666">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/yt.png" alt="YouTube Development Playlist" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Blog</title><link>https://harrand.github.io/blog/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://harrand.github.io/blog/</guid><description>2022 Ego in learning programming</description><content>&lt;h2 id="2022">2022&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="../../blog_ego_in_learning_programming">Ego in learning programming&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></content></item><item><title>Ego in learning programming</title><link>https://harrand.github.io/blog_ego_in_learning_programming/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://harrand.github.io/blog_ego_in_learning_programming/</guid><description>Introduction There are many endless debates between programmers, inside and outside of industry. Examples of these are:
Tabs vs spaces? Which editor/IDE is the best? Which operating system is best for programming? Which frontend web framework is the best? And my least favourite of them all:
What is the best programming language? There is nothing inherently harmful with these questions &amp;ndash; for the majority of sensible people, we have projects we need to complete, and the tools which we use to do the job are mostly preference.</description><content>&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are many endless debates between programmers, inside and outside of industry. Examples of these are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Tabs vs spaces?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Which editor/IDE is the best?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Which operating system is best for programming?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Which frontend web framework is the best?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>And my least favourite of them all:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>What is the best programming language?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>There is nothing inherently harmful with these questions &amp;ndash; for the majority of sensible people, we have projects we need to complete, and the tools which we use to do the job are mostly preference. Once in a while of course we come across those who take it much too seriously &amp;ndash; perhaps someone calls someone else a moron because they use Windows as opposed to a fully custom arch installation which they spent 3 weeks customising. If you were to say this wasn&amp;rsquo;t an issue worth a blog post about, I would agree!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another example of this are programming language debates. Mostly a waste of time &amp;ndash; if you fall into this trap you run the risk of spending so much time debating why C++ is the best language of all time, that you don&amp;rsquo;t actually get anything done outside of that thread.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While I was learning, I spent alot of my time in learning environments &amp;ndash; whether that be various programming discords lead by youtubers/streamers, or sites such as gamedev.net, coding subreddits or even /g/. As I moved from learning to actually building stuff, I never really left those places. I&amp;rsquo;ve kept my eye on them over the years, still sometimes learning cool new things, often helping others where I can, and seeing what kinds of conversations people have in those places. I have come to realise that the debates and battles I highlighted from before seem to be &lt;strong>increasingly common&lt;/strong> in these spaces, so much so that I am now concerned as to how much this could be preventing learners from, well&amp;hellip; learning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It got even worse when I started dabbling with YouTube streaming. I would visit other small streamers, and while the content was interesting, the chat was a complete cesspool. Piles of people taking turns spamming the chat with vitriolic arguments against each other, because someone at some point brought up that they were learning Rust instead of C++. I felt for the people who were just trying to interact with the streamer and learn, and I also felt for the streamer - it seems like they are doomed to either entirely ignore or moderate their chat from language debates for eternity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I believe these language debates are a symptom of a real issue affecting those who are learning programming - Ego.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="machismo">Machismo&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Machismo (noun) - strong or aggressive masculine pride.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Most of us are dudes. It&amp;rsquo;s tempting to go down the controvertial route: Are men more prone to ego problems than women? Is what I&amp;rsquo;m hinting at a &lt;em>male&lt;/em> problem, and it only seems so rife because there&amp;rsquo;s so many of us in this space? I&amp;rsquo;m not in a position to comment on any of this, and if I read a blog post that started yammering on about masculinity when I&amp;rsquo;m meant to be talking about programming, I&amp;rsquo;d probably close the tab and try to prevent the cringe from overwhelming me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To avoid having to worry about any of this while still being able to make my point, I will be writing the rest of this post from a male-centric perspective. Chances are you&amp;rsquo;re a man reading this, so that shouldn&amp;rsquo;t really be a problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I was starting my journey to learn programming, I started with some of the basic webdev languages at the time. That&amp;rsquo;s your HTML, CSS, JavaScript etc&amp;hellip; Those were fine and taught me valuable things, but I only chose to start learning these because that&amp;rsquo;s what people told me to do. I wanted to learn C++ because it was a &lt;em>hard&lt;/em> language to learn, because you &lt;em>need&lt;/em> to learn it to write good games, lest your project have poor performance and explode in a bloodied mess!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did want to make games. I did want to truly understand what it was like to work closer to the metal. However, with a bit of regret, I now concede that a big part of it was because it was &lt;em>intimidating&lt;/em>. It was a challenge to be conquered. When asked why I chose to start learning C++ as soon as possible, I told them how eager I was to make games, and how much I wanted to understand how my machine works from a lower-level perspective. That was all true, but I never did tell them that perhaps the biggest reason was because if I learned C++ early, that would be impressive, and set me above others.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This all occurred around 2011. I was only thirteen years old around then. How cool would I have looked to say &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m 13 and I know c++!&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s now 2022 and I&amp;rsquo;ve yet to properly ship a game in my own time, despite continuing with C++ all this time. I think that&amp;rsquo;s proof enough that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in this purely to make games.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I see people in these youtube stream chats fighting over which language is the best, I see myself flexing in favour of my own language choice back in minecraft servers. I can only be thankful that those chatlogs will never see the light of day again, lest I remember how much I was truly driven by this new form of intellectual-machismo. When I read messages from people boasting about how easy they found it to learn C++, and how they didn&amp;rsquo;t understand why everyone said it was so hard, I see the same flex that I too was guilty of doing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I wasted alot of my time back then. I think more and more people are making the same mistake, and none of us are doing anything about it. University entirely ignores it, I&amp;rsquo;ve no idea how bootcamps deal with it, and programming communities mostly sit back and wait for these silly debates to get too heated before ultimately dispersing it &amp;ndash; at that point the damage is done.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="real-programmers-use-vim">Real programmers use vim&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Just to be clear - my point in this blog is that I believe that learners are more and more commonly falling into the trap of entering ego-measuring contests under the guise of &amp;ldquo;debates&amp;rdquo; over which programming language is the best, or why vim is the ultimate editor and you&amp;rsquo;re an idiot if you don&amp;rsquo;t already know all of the keybinds off-by-heart while learning how to do fizzbuzz in C.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once a while in these programming discords, someone wise comes down and asks questions which invite the reader to actually think about what they&amp;rsquo;re saying:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>You said: &amp;ldquo;I respect an osdev more than a webdev.&amp;rdquo; Why?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;What exactly is wrong with vscode?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;What else do you think is good about this code snippet, aside from performance?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Sometimes this stifles the silliness in the conversation and things return to normality &amp;ndash; It&amp;rsquo;s absolutely possible to discuss these topics in a productive and useful way, but there comes a point where people buy too much into it, except that with a bit of self-reflection things can come back down to non-heated chatter.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-solution">What is the solution?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re a learner, and you think you might be guilty of this, that&amp;rsquo;s okay. If someone who&amp;rsquo;s been in the industry for years tells me they didn&amp;rsquo;t fall into this trap, I would struggle to believe them. I definitely let things get to my head too much in the earlier stages, and I might continue to sometimes make that mistake. I try to avoid it, but sometimes you have a moment of weakness and just can&amp;rsquo;t help yourself.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;ve read all this and are completely lost and dumbfounded as to how someone can get off on some weird &amp;lsquo;valor&amp;rsquo; that comes with a preference in programming language/OS/framework, fair enough. I would be interested to know from those who have never seen any of this in the wild, and think I might be just going on an inane rant. I come from a engine-dev background, perhaps that is an outlier when it comes to this kind of issue.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The next time you see someone talk trash about your favourite programming language, or belittle someone else who made the same choice as you, consider not wasting your time on it. If you&amp;rsquo;re the other way around and look down on those who go into webdev, or don&amp;rsquo;t write code using a charged needle, I urge you to think about how productive you&amp;rsquo;ve actually been, even if you&amp;rsquo;ve been making all the correct decisions all this time.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Projects</title><link>https://harrand.github.io/projects/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://harrand.github.io/projects/</guid><description>Topaz Engine, 2015-Present, Language: C++
Topaz is a 3D graphics engine. It supports linux/windows and can be configured to use opengl/vulkan under-the-hood.
As of writing, the most recent version is Topaz 3.5.
Red Nightmare 2 Topaz Game, 2022-Present, Language: C++
Red Nightmare 2 is a complete rewrite of the original game, using Topaz 3.5, currently in development.
The game is a 2D action roguelite. There will be multiple playable characters, but the player originally controls a sorceress named Akhara.</description><content>&lt;h1 id="topaz">Topaz&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/tz.png" alt="Topaz" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
Engine, 2015-Present, Language: C++&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Topaz is a 3D graphics engine. It supports linux/windows and can be configured to use opengl/vulkan under-the-hood.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As of writing, the most recent version is Topaz 3.5.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Harrand/Topaz">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/gh.svg" alt="Github Repository" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL6PSLdrGGe8I67_i6mNk8IUmOsP85Vhll">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/yt.png" alt="YouTube Development Playlist" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://harrand.github.io/Topaz/">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/doc.png" alt="Documentation" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="red-nightmare-2">Red Nightmare 2&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/red_nightmare.png" alt="Red Nightmare 2" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
Topaz Game, 2022-Present, Language: C++&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Red Nightmare 2 is a complete rewrite of the original game, using Topaz 3.5, currently in development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The game is a 2D action roguelite. There will be multiple playable characters, but the player originally controls a sorceress named Akhara. You must navigate through the story levels, defeating monsters on the way using Akhara&amp;rsquo;s fireballs. Alternatively, you can play procedural levels, which are randomly generated, and last forever until you die.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Harrand/Red-Nightmare">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/gh.svg" alt="Github Repository" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PL6PSLdrGGe8JU5bsKL4Kohhi7e5aFSzTu">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/yt.png" alt="YouTube Development Playlist" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="parched">Parched&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/parched.png" alt="Parched" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
Topaz Game, 2022, Language: C++&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Parched is a 2D physics-based sample game using Topaz 3.3. You spawn balls in a limited-size world.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Harrand/Parched">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/gh.svg" alt="Github Repository" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="comparison-of-some-occlusion-culling-algorithms-used-in-modern-game-engine-development">Comparison of some occlusion culling algorithms used in modern game engine development&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Paper, 2019, 3D Graphics&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Research project consisting of CPU-centric occlusion-culling approaches using Topaz, aswell as a writeup dissertation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Compares a software-renderered occlusion culling approach against an older approach based on potentially-visible sets of nodes. Both are implemented in separate forks of Topaz 1.0. This was a dissertation for university.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Regrettably, the paper does not touch upon GPU-based approaches, which have become more popular now.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Harrand/Dissertation">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/gh.svg" alt="Github Repository" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="amethyst">Amethyst&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/am.png" alt="Amethyst" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
Library, 2018-2019, Language: C++&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Amethyst is a cross-platform basic networking library. It is very low-level, dealing only in sockets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Harrand/Amethyst">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/gh.svg" alt="Github Repository" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="red-nightmare">Red Nightmare&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/red_nightmare.png" alt="Red Nightmare" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
Topaz Game, 2018, Language: C++&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Red Nightmare is an old sample game using Topaz 1.0. You play as a sorceress aswell as her magical elemental orb, but you are attacked by ghosts. You also have the power of telekinesis, which you can use to drag ghosts out of your way or into their doom.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The orb has different effects depending on its current elemental type. The fiery orb deals massive damage, the frost orb slows nearby ghosts, and the void orb sucks in ghosts and consumes them, growing in size.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After killing enough ghosts, a boss battle begins against Nightmare. Nightmare is a malevolent powerful ghost who can only be stopped with the combination of the orb and your telekinesis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Harrand/Red-Nightmare/tree/Topaz1.0">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/gh.svg" alt="Github Repository" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/Ps6-L03zkuA">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/yt.png" alt="YouTube Development Playlist" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="maze-darwinism">Maze Darwinism&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/maze_darwinism.png" alt="Maze Darwinism" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
Application, 2018, Language: Java&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maze Darwinism was an application which displayed a maze which would be solved automatically. The solution would evolve via natural selection until the maze was solved.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The natural selection was implemented in pure Java, and the graphics done in javax.swing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Harrand/Maze-Darwinism">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/gh.svg" alt="Github Repository" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h1 id="the-chimera-of-gold">The Chimera of Gold&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/chimera_banner.png" alt="Chimera of Gold" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
Unity Game, 2018, Language: C#&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Chimera of Gold was a group-project at university where we created a 3D board-game in Unity. I was the group leader. It is based off of the ancient Indian game known as Pachisi.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is a mountain-climbing board game for 2-5 players. Each player starts with 5 pawns at different camps at the base of the mountain. Your turn begins with a dice roll, which decides the number of tiles you can move at once.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Obstacles stand in your way. You can get past them by rolling the dice to move exactly onto its tile. Once you do this, you can move the obstacle to almost anywhere on the map. Isolate the obstacle to clear your path, or go out of your way to place them in the path of your opponents! If you land on the same tile as an opponents pawn, you send that pawn back to its base camp. You can also do this to your own pawns, so take care!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a golden tile at the summit of the mountain. A player wins when all five of their pawns reach the golden tile.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/Harrand/The_Chimera_of_Gold">
&lt;img src="https://harrand.github.io/gh.svg" alt="Github Repository" class="left" style="border-radius: 8px; width: 2%; display: inline;" />
&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr></content></item></channel></rss>